George P. Kontoudis

3242 Kim Engineering Building, College Park, MD 20742, USA

★ www.georgekontoudis.com ⋈ kont@umd.edu ♦ Updated: May 30, 2022

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the intersection of robotics, control theory, and machine learning. I am particularly interested in how learning algorithms and control theory can enable multi-agent systems to efficiently collaborate with minimal information exchange for robotic navigation and exploration tasks.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE	
Postdoctoral Research Associate (MRC Fellow), University of Maryland Motion and Teaming Lab, Maryland Robotics Center (PI: Michael Otte)	Jan 2022–present
Graduate Research Assistant, Virginia Tech Center for Marine Autonomy & Robotics (PI: Daniel J. Stilwell) Computational Multiphysics Systems Laboratory (PI: Tomonari Furukawa)	Aug 2018–Dec 2021 Aug 2016–Jul 2018
Undergraduate Research Assistant, National Technical University of Athens Control Systems Laboratory (PI: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos)	Apr 2014–Mar 2016
Founder & Research Associate, OpenBionics	Sep 2014–present
EDUCATION	
PhD in Electrical Engineering, Virginia Tech Advisor: Daniel J. Stilwell Dissertation Title: "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration GPA: 3.94/4.00	2018–2021 tion"
MSc in Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech Advisors: Tomonari Furukawa & Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis Thesis Title: "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation" GPA: 4.00/4.00	2016–2018
Diploma in Mechanical Engineering, National Technical University of Athens Advisor: Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos Thesis Title: "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand"	2012–2016
BSc in Mechanical Engineering, University of West Attica	2005–2010
TEACHING EXPERIENCE	
Graduate Teaching Assistant, Virginia Tech Department of Mechanical Engineering	Fall 2016, Spring 2017
AWARDS & HONORS	
Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS) Pioneer (Acceptance Rate: 35%) Maryland Robotics Center (MRC) Postdoctoral Fellowship 5 × IEEE Student Travel Support (IROS, ACC, CDC) 2 × Virginia Tech GSA Travel Fund Award (Humanoids, ICORR) NSF Student Travel Grant (WuWNet) NTUA Thomaideion Award Hackaday Prize, 2 nd place among 900 projects	2022 2022 2015, 2019–2021 2019, 2020 2019 2016 2015
Debatalan Innonation Assemble 18 plans	2015

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Robotdalen Innovation Award, 1st place

Mechanical Engineer, Sychem S.A.	Oct 2010–Aug 2015
Aircraft Maintenance Engineer Trainee, Olympic Aviation	May 2008–Jan 2010

2015

Preprints [P1]

[P1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Fully Decentralized, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Multi-Agent Federated Learning," *arXiv preprint*, 2022. (*under review*)

Referred Journal Publications [J4]

- [J1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Stephen Krauss, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Model-Based Learning of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance for Marine Robots," *Robotics and Autonomous Systems*, 2021.
- [J2] Geng Gao, Mojtaba Shahmohammadi, Lucas Gerez, **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, "On Differential Mechanisms for Underactuated, Lightweight, Adaptive Prosthetic Hands," *Frontiers in Neurorobotics*, 2021.
- [J3] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Kinodynamic Motion Planning with Continuous-Time Q-Learning: An Online, Model-Free, and Safe Navigation Framework," *IEEE Trans. on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*, 2019.
- [J4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Tomonari Furukawa, "An Adaptive Actuation Mechanism for Anthropomorphic Robot Hands," *Frontiers in Robotics and AI*, 2019.

Referred Conference Publications [C12]

- [C1] Josh Netter, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Bounded Rational RRT-QX: Multi-Agent Motion Planning in Dynamic Human-Like Environments Using Cognitive Hierarchy and Q-Learning," *IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)*, Austin, USA, 2021.
- [C2] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [C3] Minas Liarokapis, **George P. Kontoudis**, "Teaching Robotic and Biomechatronic Concepts with a Gripper Design Project and a Grasping and Manipulation Competition," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021.
- [C4] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "Prediction of Acoustic Communication Performance in Marine Robots Using Model-Based Kriging," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, New Orleans, USA, 2021.
- [C5] Gal Gorjup, **George P. Kontoudis**, Anany Dwivedi, Geng Gao, Saori Matsunaga, Toshisada Mariyama, Bruce MacDonald, and Minas Liarokapis "Combining Programming by Demonstration with Path Optimization and Local Replanning to Facilitate the Execution of Assembly Tasks," *IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man and Cybernetics (SMC)*, Toronto, Canada, 2020.
- [C6] **George P. Kontoudis**, Zirui Xu, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020.
- [C7] **George P. Kontoudis**, Daniel J. Stilwell, "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM Int. Conf. on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019.
- [C8] George P. Kontoudis, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [C9] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS Inter. Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019.
- [C10] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019.
- [C11] Kyriakos D. Tsoukalas, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, "Active-Bayesian Learning for Cooperation Connectivity in Dynamic Cyber-Physical-Human Systems," *IEEE Symposium on Adaptive Dynamic Programming and Reinforcement Learning (ADPRL)*, Honolulu, USA, 2017.
- [C12] George P. Kontoudis, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Hamburg, Germany, 2015.

Chapters in Edited Volumes [V1]

[V1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis, Zirui Xu, "RRT-QX: Real-Time Kinodynamic Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments with Continuous-Time Reinforcement Learning," in *Brain and Cognitive Intelligence: Control in Robotics*, B. Wei (Ed.), Taylor & Francis Group, CRC Press, 2022.

Referred Workshop Publications [W1]

[W1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Scalable Multi-Robot Active Exploration," *Robotics: Science and Systems (RSS) Pioneers Work-shop*, New York City, USA, June 2022.

Theses [T3]

- [T1] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration," *Doctoral Dissertation, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2021.
- [T2] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Master Thesis, Virginia Tech*, USA, December 2018.
- [T3] **George P. Kontoudis**, "Design and Development of an Underactuated, Anthropomorphic Robot Hand," *Diploma Thesis*, *National Technical University of Athens*, March 2016. (in Greek)

Technical Reports [R2]

- [R1] **George P. Kontoudis**, Minas Liarokapis, Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Anthropomorphic, Light-Weight Prosthetic Hands," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, October 2015.
- [R2] Agisilaos G. Zisimatos, Minas Liarokapis, Christoforos I. Mavrogiannis, **George P. Kontoudis**, Kostas J. Kyriakopoulos, "How to Create Affordable, Modular, Light-Weight, Underactuated, Compliant Robot Hand," *Control Systems Lab, National Technical University of Athens*, Athens, Greece, January 2015.

TALKS & PRESENTATIONS

- · "Communication-Aware, Scalable Gaussian Processes for Decentralized Exploration" *Bradley Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2021. [PhD Defense]
- · "Decentralized Nested Gaussian Processes for Multi-Robot Systems," *IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)*, Xi'an, China, 2021. [Virtual Presentation]
- · "Online, Model-Free Motion Planning in Dynamic Environments: An Intermittent, Finite Horizon Approach with Continuous-Time Q-Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Denver, USA, 2020. **[Rapid-Interactive Presentation]**
- · "A Comparison of Kriging and Cokriging for Estimation of Underwater Acoustic Communication Performance," *ACM International Conference on Underwater Networks and Systems (WuWNet)*, Atlanta, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," Workshop on New Challenges in Humanoid Grasping and Manipulation in IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids), Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Oral Presentation Invited Talk]
- · "An Adaptive, Humanlike Robot Hand with Selective Interdigitation: Towards Robust Grasping and Dexterous, In-Hand Manipulation," *IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Robust Kinodynamic Motion Planning using Model-Free Game-Theoretic Learning," *American Control Conference (ACC)*, Philadelphia, USA, 2019. [Oral Presentation]
- · "A Compliant, Underactuated Finger for Anthropomorphic Hands," *IEEE/RAS-EMBS International Conference on Rehabilitation Robotics (ICORR)*, Toronto, Canada, 2019. [Poster Presentation]
- · "Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Grasping and In-Hand Manipulation," *Department of Mechanical Engineering, Virginia Tech*, Blacksburg, USA, December 2018. [Master's Defense]
- · "Evaluation Strategies of Adaptive, Anthropomorphic Robot Hands for Dexterous In-Hand Manipulation: Early Results," *National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)*, USA, 2018. [Invited Talk]
- · "Open-Source, Anthropomorphic, Underactuated Robot Hands with a Selectively Lockable Differential Mechanism: Towards Affordable Prostheses," *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, Hamburg, Germany, 2015. [Oral Presentation]

SERVICE ACTIVITIES

Conference Organizing Committees	
Online Platform Chair, Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL)	2022
Reviewer, Journals	
IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems	2019–202
IEEE Transactions on Robotics	2020
IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering	2020, 202.
IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics	2020
IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man and Cybernetics: Systems	202.
IEEE Computational Intelligence Magazine	2020
IEEE Control Systems Letters	2019, 2020
IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters	2019, 2022
IEEE Robotics & Automation Magazine	202
Autonomous Robots	202
Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence	202
Frontiers in Robotics and AI	202
Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications	202.
International Journal of Advanced Robotic Systems	2015, 201
Reviewer, Conferences	
American Control Conference (ACC)	2018–202
IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA)	2018–202
IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)	2018–202.
IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)	2019, 202
IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering (CASE)	201
IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)	201
IEEE International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics (BioRob)	2018, 2020, 202
European Control Conference (ECC)	202.
Mediterranean Conference on Control and Automation (MED)	2016
ENTORING	
PhD Students	
Joshua Netter, Georgia Institute of Technology [C1] Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	2020–presen
Master's Students	
Alkesh Kumar Srivastava, University of Maryland Advisor: Michael Otte	2022–presen
Zirui Xu, Georgia Institute of Technology [C6], [V1]	2018–202
Advisor: Kyriakos G. Vamvoudakis	
Currently: PhD student, University of Michigan	